<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>fnl en España - Miscellaneous</title><link href="https://fnl.es/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://fnl.es/feeds/miscellaneous.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://fnl.es/</id><updated>2021-10-04T00:00:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>Lean, generative cultures and how to probe for them</title><link href="https://fnl.es/lean-generative-cultures-and-how-to-probe-for-them.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-10-04T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-10-04T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Florian Leitner</name></author><id>tag:fnl.es,2021-10-04:/lean-generative-cultures-and-how-to-probe-for-them.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Performance-oriented organizations that value transparency and empower
their workforce were baptized &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://qualitysafety.bmj.com/content/13/suppl_2/ii22"&gt;generative
cultures&lt;/a&gt; by
Ron Westrum in 2004. This article will describe why
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.lean.org/explore-lean/what-is-lean/"&gt;lean&lt;/a&gt;, generative
cultures might interest the reader and point out the &amp;quot;secrete sauce&amp;quot; in
creating them: transforming &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://cdn.csu.edu.au/__data/assets/pdf_file/0008/917018/Eight-Behaviors-for-Smarter-Teams-2.pdf"&gt;behavior and
communication&lt;/a&gt;.
Note that despite having &amp;quot;lean&amp;quot; in the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Performance-oriented organizations that value transparency and empower
their workforce were baptized &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://qualitysafety.bmj.com/content/13/suppl_2/ii22"&gt;generative
cultures&lt;/a&gt; by
Ron Westrum in 2004. This article will describe why
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.lean.org/explore-lean/what-is-lean/"&gt;lean&lt;/a&gt;, generative
cultures might interest the reader and point out the &amp;quot;secrete sauce&amp;quot; in
creating them: transforming &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://cdn.csu.edu.au/__data/assets/pdf_file/0008/917018/Eight-Behaviors-for-Smarter-Teams-2.pdf"&gt;behavior and
communication&lt;/a&gt;.
Note that despite having &amp;quot;lean&amp;quot; in the title, the text will deliberately
ignore Lean's &amp;quot;customer value&amp;quot; aspect, focusing on the soft skills
(respect and teamwork) and &lt;strong&gt;Kaizen&lt;/strong&gt; (continuous improvement) instead.
Finally, this post concludes with a reasonable way to probe if an
organization has adopted such a culture, no matter if you are inside or
outside that org.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to Westrum, generative cultures place their utmost value on
the flow of information. One might say they value &lt;strong&gt;transparency&lt;/strong&gt; above
all else. The &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://openstax.org/books/principles-management/pages/3-3-the-industrial-revolution"&gt;industrial
revolution&lt;/a&gt;
came around by ensuring that data flows from the edges (workers/actors)
to the centers (leaders). Even Napoleon's success as a military leader
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://core.ac.uk/download/pdf/36698436.pdf"&gt;has been attributed&lt;/a&gt;
to Napoleon creating an efficient flow of intelligence back to central
command and control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generative cultures ensure the &lt;em&gt;reverse&lt;/em&gt; flow of information back to the
edges, too: In a self-evident example, imagine workers having access to
real-time data about the sale of each type of product made in their
factory. That would allow those workers to make &lt;strong&gt;Agile&lt;/strong&gt; production
decisions (i.e., swiftly and independently) without including a long and
tedious communication chain through company silos and hierarchies. The
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://hbr.org/1990/11/how-i-learned-to-let-my-workers-lead"&gt;(sausage) factory
example&lt;/a&gt;
also highlights the lean, bottom-up nature of such cultures: Namely, an
organization's ability to build a workforce that can make decisions at
the edges instead of relying on centralized decision-making structures.
That requires that critical information gets to those workers who might
be taking corrective actions based on it without impediment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond transparency, to cite Westrum, generative cultures exhibit high
cooperation and teamwork with shared accountability, encourage bridging
across organizational silos, follow the practice of Kaizen (continuous
improvement), and provide fertile grounds for novel ideas to thrive. It
requires an organization with high levels of trust among its people and
leaders able to coach their teams on handling disagreements and conflict
to unlock these benefits, thereby &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://itrevolution.com/agile-conversations/"&gt;transforming the organization's
culture&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, the &amp;quot;secret sauce&amp;quot; is all about building engagement and
dependability by gradually giving the workforce more decision-making
authority. Information gets &amp;quot;stuck&amp;quot; if any manager in the company's
reporting chain first has to &amp;quot;call the shots&amp;quot;: Every time that happens,
in the best case, a delay is introduced - and in the worst case,
information is lost. Ultimately, an organization's ability to make the
most optimal decisions and therefore reach the best possible &lt;em&gt;business
outcomes&lt;/em&gt; depends on surfacing the relevant data in time at those places
where a change needs to transpire (which is, most often, at the edges).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Building such an enabled workforce requires a leadership team that
trusts and respects its people.
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.leanblog.org/2013/02/toyota-respect-for-people-or-humanity-and-lean/"&gt;Respect&lt;/a&gt;
refers to one of the five Lean values: Having a psychologically safe
environment where leaders coach their teams in decision-making while
providing all the necessary data. And &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.tablegroup.com/the-five-dysfunctions-of-a-team-trust/"&gt;(Lencioni's vulnerability-based)
trust&lt;/a&gt;,
among other things, implies that the leader is willing to rely on the
team to make the right decisions instead of the leader making those
decisions unilaterally. In other words, it requires leaders to face
their ego and overcome inner fears by &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uOiP4mJwqE0"&gt;conceding decision-making powers
to their reports (&amp;quot;Brave New
Work&amp;quot;)&lt;/a&gt;. Furthermore, it
requires a leadership behavior that allows curiosity and collaboration
to foster. That, in turn, needs managers with a broad range of abilities
and a coaching mindset:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The ability to create a psychologically safe learning environment and
teach &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www-personal.umich.edu/~mrother/The_Improvement_Kata.html"&gt;continual
self-improvement&lt;/a&gt;;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The ability to coach people on how to approach problems in a
data-driven way to generate optimal solutions &lt;em&gt;as a team&lt;/em&gt;;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Making all relevant information available while eradicating &amp;quot;the
undiscussable&amp;quot; (Anything that a team should talk about but only
get addressed in hallways, 1on1s, or among smaller groups.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plus all the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://rework.withgoogle.com/guides/managers-identify-what-makes-a-great-manager/steps/learn-about-googles-manager-research/"&gt;&amp;quot;standard&amp;quot;
ingredients&lt;/a&gt;
that make up a great manager, such as providing structure &amp;amp;
clarity, accountability, meaning, and impact.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the reader might agree with all of the above, it can be a long
path for an untrained person to acquire those skills. When I first
encountered these ideas, I believed that I was practicing them already,
only to discover that I was (and in some areas very much still am)
nowhere close after a more detailed introspection of my behavior.
Anyhow, the above description and links should provide the interested
reader with more than sufficient material to take that path. Instead, in
this blog post, I would like to conclude with an exciting way to probe
if you, your team, your company, or even the company you are
interviewing with is building a lean, generative culture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The test is a short set of questions that you can ask, in any context,
as a self-test, when talking to your future manager or out of general
curiosity:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Transparency&lt;/strong&gt; and information flow: People should be willing to
disagree when they see things differently and openly share how
they come to their views. Can you give some examples of how your
team navigates disagreements and makes decisions? Can you explain
how you increase teamwork among your reports?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Curiosity&lt;/strong&gt; and continuous improvement: Teams should have a mutual
learning mindset and be eager to improve continually. Can you
provide concrete examples of how your team improves itself and
learns together? What is the most exciting thing your team worked
on or researched recently, and what did you learn?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accountability&lt;/strong&gt; and dependability: Everyone on the team should be
encouraged to take full responsibility for their words, actions,
and results. Can you give examples of how you ensure that your
people can depend on each other? How do you motivate people to
participate in meetings, take on responsibilities, and grow?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Core values&lt;/strong&gt; and more Kaizen: What do you see as the
organization's most significant strengths and weaknesses, and how
are you acting on those insights?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above questions are the &amp;quot;probes&amp;quot; I have designed to keep asking
myself and track if I am improving as a leader. While I at least believe
that the remaining core lean, generative culture values (compassion,
respect, and trust) must be present if you can answer the above
questions satisfactorily. I am sure the questions are not pixel perfect,
so I would greatly welcome all constructive criticism if you see
cleverer ways to design this test.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="Miscellaneous"></category><category term="management"></category></entry><entry><title>MobileMe vs. SugarSync vs. DropBox</title><link href="https://fnl.es/mobileme-vs-sugarsync-vs-dropbox.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2009-05-26T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2009-05-26T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Florian Leitner</name></author><id>tag:fnl.es,2009-05-26:/mobileme-vs-sugarsync-vs-dropbox.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I now have tested MobileMe, SugarSync, and DropBox for quite a while to
decide which service to buy for syncing my “electronic life” between my
Macs (soon I’ll be managing two OSX Server blades, one Mini, and two
MBPs!). After this period, there is no doubt to me: I …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I now have tested MobileMe, SugarSync, and DropBox for quite a while to
decide which service to buy for syncing my “electronic life” between my
Macs (soon I’ll be managing two OSX Server blades, one Mini, and two
MBPs!). After this period, there is no doubt to me: I’m syncing my iCal
calendars and Address Book content via Google, my bookmarks with XMarks,
and everything else via DropBox.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MobileMe’s iDisk is nothing more than a pain and a piece of junk, which
I honestly did not expect. After all the problems they had last year
launching Me.com, I thought they would have by now created a working
service. But the iDisk and syncing my PIM (Personal Information Manager
- I still use Yojimbo, as Evernote’s and Together’s handling of
encryption are pure patched add-ons) was just a [bad] joke: You even
need to buy extra software if you want to do file syncing, as iDisk’s
“offline” sync is so slow and error prone I could not believe Apple
dares to offer something like that. So you need to either use Lingon and
rsync to sync to your online mode iDisk which doesn’t win a medal for
simplicity, or buy something like ChronoSync - and that takes hours
(!!!) to ensure 10 GB of data in about 30-40k Files are synced, &lt;strong&gt;every
time&lt;/strong&gt;. All the more, ChronoSync may be the fastest and safest syncer in
the wild! What finally got me mad was the sync agent using 90% CPU all
of the time, at times virtually locking you out of your own machine,
while performing almost nothing. Finally, if you ever try to navigate
that online iDisk, get yourself a cup of tea, you will have plenty of
time to drink it up until that file is open…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compared to SugarSync, DropBox with its simplicity and real versioning
of files is significantly better performing than SugarSync, espcially if
we talk upload and real volume, and if you ever tried SugarSync, it is a
resource hugger (not as bad as iDisk, but it will stop your workflow).
So in the end the choice for me was based on “mutual exclusion”, there
is simply still no service that can hold the candle to DropBox - and
just got me Pro account. As I am writing this, I am syncing up dozens of
gigs of data to my 50 GB DropBox, and I hardly notice it happening!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, if you get yourself an account for DropBox, either the free 2 GB or
a full Pro account, I would appreciate if you register via &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.getdropbox.com/referrals/NTE0NTA0OTk"&gt;this link&lt;/a&gt;,
as it creates me some 500 MB extra space for referring you :o).&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="Miscellaneous"></category><category term="apple"></category><category term="cloud storage"></category></entry><entry><title>News, Swines &amp; Pigs</title><link href="https://fnl.es/news-swines-pigs.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2009-04-30T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2009-04-30T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Florian Leitner</name></author><id>tag:fnl.es,2009-04-30:/news-swines-pigs.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Usually, I prefer to steer free from the day-to-day mainstream news, yet
even I have to accept a low level of &amp;quot;noise&amp;quot; if I want to know at least
something about the most significant things going on. However, currently
I get the overwhelming feeling that the whole news world is …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Usually, I prefer to steer free from the day-to-day mainstream news, yet
even I have to accept a low level of &amp;quot;noise&amp;quot; if I want to know at least
something about the most significant things going on. However, currently
I get the overwhelming feeling that the whole news world is grunting and
snorting like a pigsty. You guessed it, I am concerned about all this
&amp;quot;swine flu&amp;quot; reporting going on. As can be easily demonstrated, this
whole &amp;quot;pandemic alert&amp;quot; and panic-making has gone completely out of
proportion. It is yet another example of how ridiculous news agencies
exaggerate or even blur the facts, and this attitude might be much more
lethal than most biological illnesses if measured by its indirect
impact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of, some flu virus classification: There are three types of
influenza virus: A, B, and C. B and C play only very minor roles as they
mutate slower, are less virulent, and affect far less species. Usually,
when talking about a flu virus, type A is implied. Type A influenza then
is further categorized by the HxNx nomenclature. The H refers to the
hemagglutinin (HA) lectin and the N to the neuroaminidase (NA)
glycoprotein. Both are found on the outside coat of the virus particle.
HA mediates the virus' binding to target cells, while NA is responsible
for the release of progeny virus from infected host cells. The numbers
denote the antibody response of the virus, ordered by historic discovery
- meaning, a virus with the same H/N number is identified by the same
&lt;em&gt;type&lt;/em&gt; of antibodies, which form part of your immune system/defense. HA
and NA are essential for the virulence (the relative ability to cause
disease) in terms of infectiveness and the epidemic capabilities of the
strain. H1N1 denotes the class of flu virus HA/NA proteins that is the
most commonly found form in human influenza. Our immune system defends
us by recognizing mainly those two proteins (the &amp;quot;antigenes&amp;quot;) through
our antibodies. This means, from a pure immuno-defense point of view,
this kind of strain is the most well known to the human body and immune
system. This is one of the reasons why the new Hong Kong avian flu, with
its H5N1 composition, is much more virulent than the current H1N1 swine
flu or any other &amp;quot;regular&amp;quot; flu.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Endemic states and lethal properties: H1N1 most deadly appearance and
the worst pandemic in modern human history was what we now know as the
&amp;quot;Spanish Flu&amp;quot; in 1918; This specific influenza virus transformed its
endemic properties (the ability to propagate within one kind of species,
in this case birds) to a panzootic state (affecting animals including
humans - epizootic would be the intermediate state that does not affect
humans). Note that this pandemic occurred during WW I, largely
facilitating its spread. In general, any kind of virus capable of
overcoming the species barrier is potentially more dangerous, as it is
likely to carry genetic material and protein structures the newly
infected species has never seen before, therefor being much more
virulent and lethal than the existing endemic strains. However, the
Spanish Flu killed somewhere around 20 million people (taking
conservative, low estimates), and its symptoms were so strong it was
often misdiagnosed as some much more severe infection. Apart from the
HA/NA properties already mentioned, there is the actual RNA (viruses
commonly use RNA instead of DNA to carry their genetic information) that
a virus uses to encode its proteins and other functions that are
important to the survival and impact of a virus. Our immune defense
looks for RNA sequences those are different to any sequence found in our
body and &amp;quot;destroys&amp;quot; those foreign sequences by cleaving the strands into
non-functional pieces with the help of so-called RNases. For this to
work, the immune system therefor has to identify the RNA [as foreign].
But a strand of RNA coming from another species might actually contain
nucleotide base sequences our immune system does not recognize (because
it only recognizes already &lt;em&gt;known&lt;/em&gt; foreign sequences), making the virus
much more lethal. This process of changing the RNA and protein
configuration is amplified by two related mechanisms called &amp;quot;genetic
drift&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;antigenic shift&amp;quot;. In the case of the Spanish flu, the RNA
was very &amp;quot;new&amp;quot; to the human's immune system and had a very high mutation
rate: how often the RNA sequence changes, roughly the meaning of the
aforementioned genetic drift and antigenic shift. On the contrary, the
new &amp;quot;Mexican&amp;quot; swine flu virus has a very similar RNA composition to
regular virus strains found in humans, i.e. it does not appear to be
significantly more leathal than any other flu. The only known difference
to the regular flu circulating in humans is that it seems to affect more
younger than older people, possibly due to the fact that older people's
immune systems already have &amp;quot;seen&amp;quot; a similar version of this virus some
time ago and therefor have antibodies that recognize the HA/NA
glycoproteins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now compare this swine flu against any regular flu by numbers: The
regular flu kills about 250,000 to &lt;em&gt;half a million&lt;/em&gt; people &lt;em&gt;per year&lt;/em&gt;.
This overhyped swine flu managed to kill &lt;em&gt;eight&lt;/em&gt; (8!) humans so far and
it has been confirmed to have infected about 150 people worldwide (WHO
data, 29th of April, 2009). I.e., on a daily average about a
&lt;strong&gt;thousand times more&lt;/strong&gt; people die from the regular flu than this new
strain. Regular flu is almost continuously spreading somewhere in the
world, i.e., if the WHO took this into account, we would be living in a
nearly constant influenza pandemic. The swine flu just now made it to
the last stage before &lt;em&gt;even being defined&lt;/em&gt; as a WHO &amp;quot;pandemic&amp;quot;: There
must be a few known infections in at least two countries. Recall this
definition and check the real numbers when somebody is talking about a
new &amp;quot;pandemic&amp;quot;. The infection with swine flu seems to be no more lethal
than with any other flu, so your chances of dying from the swine flu
outside of Mexico are so marginal it makes no sense to take them into
account, while if you do go to Mexico, all you seriously need to do is
make sure your current health state is good enough to survive any flu
anywhere, which is much more prevalent and 1,000 times more likely to
kill you by a global statistic&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; But the main point is: there is
nothing dangerous or wrong about going to Mexico, at least concerning
the flu. I would be much more worried about drug gangsters and hijackers
there if I were you: They managed to kill several thousands of people
this year alone already. In other words, the WHO rulings and
suggestions, that are close to ridiculous given the circumstances,
combined with the media hype are about to isolate Mexico from the world,
which leads me to my final and most important point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general, this &amp;quot;pig-hyped&amp;quot; flu without any review of its background,
no factual content, and exclusively based on beliefs and propaganda has
only one really worrisome influence: it is weakening and isolating
Mexico, both socially and economically. Our ignorance to real facts are
estimated to cost Mexico &lt;em&gt;City&lt;/em&gt; (&amp;quot;D.F.&amp;quot;) alone around $88 million &lt;em&gt;per
day&lt;/em&gt;, and this figure will need huge updates for the crash Mexico's main
(legal) economic sector, tourism, will suffer, plus the costs incurred
on the country as a whole. This number will be similar to or more likely
even exceed the daily cost of the U.S. oil war in Irak (estimated to
about $250 million, in case you didn't know) - the only good news being
that instead of about 100 (direct, not counting the indirect toll, which
is estimated to be around five times higher) deaths per day, the swine
flu's daily death toll is still below one. In other words, the combined
direct and indirect negative impact of this insubstantial media hype on
a close to imaginary &amp;quot;Mexican Flu&amp;quot; will cost and destroy much more lives
than the virus itself most likely ever will have been capable of. Media
propaganda crusades against a country nowadays have the same
socioeconomic impact as the largest &amp;quot;real&amp;quot; war in decades if measured by
the daily cost. Keep this in mind the next time you read news about
swines from pigs.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="Miscellaneous"></category><category term="politics"></category></entry></feed>